<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
  
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="./xdoc.xsl"?>
<document url="geometry.html">

  <properties>
    <title>The Commons Math User Guide - Geometry</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="11 Geometry">
      <subsection name="11.1 Overview" href="overview">
        <p>
           The geometry package provides classes useful for many physical simulations
           in Euclidean spaces, like vectors and rotations in 3D, as well as on the
           sphere. It also provides a general implementation of Binary Space Partitioning
           Trees (BSP trees).
        </p>
        <p>
           All supported type of spaces (Euclidean 3D, Euclidean 2D, Euclidean 1D, 2-Sphere
           and 1-Sphere) provide dedicated classes that represent complex regions of the
           space as shown in the following table:
        </p>
        <p>
          <table border="1" align="center">
          <tr BGCOLOR="#CCCCFF"><td colspan="2"><font size="+1">Regions</font></td></tr>
          <tr BGCOLOR="#EEEEFF"><font size="+1"><td>Space</td><td>Region</td></font></tr>
          <tr><td>Euclidean 1D</td><td><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/oned/IntervalsSet.html">IntervalsSet</a></td></tr>
          <tr><td>Euclidean 2D</td><td><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/twod/PolygonsSet.html">PolygonsSet</a></td></tr>
          <tr><td>Euclidean 3D</td><td><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/threed/PolyhedronsSet.html">PolyhedronsSet</a></td></tr>
          <tr><td>1-Sphere</td><td><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/spherical/oned/ArcsSet.html">ArcsSet</a></td></tr>
          <tr><td>2-Sphere</td><td><a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/spherical/twod/SphericalPolygonsSet.html">SphericalPolygonsSet</a></td></tr>
          </table>
        </p>
        <p>
          All these regions share common features. Regions can be defined from several non-connected parts.
          As an example, one PolygonsSet instance in Euclidean 2D (i.e. the plane) can represent a region composed
          of several separated polygons separate from each other. They also support regions containing holes. As an example
          a SphericalPolygonsSet on the 2-Sphere can represent a land mass on the Earth with an interior sea, where points
          on this sea would not be considered to belong to the land mass. Of course more complex models can also be represented
          and it is possible to define for example one region composed of several continents, with interior sea containing
          separate islands, some of which having lakes, which may have smaller island ... In the infinite Euclidean spaces,
          regions can have infinite parts. for example in 1D (i.e. along a line), one can define an interval starting at
          abscissa 3 and extending up to infinity. This is also possible in 2D and 3D. For all spaces, regions without any
          boundaries are also possible so one can define the whole space or the empty region.
        </p>
        <p>
          The classical set operations are available in all cases: union, intersection, symmetric difference (exclusive or),
          difference, complement. There are also region predicates (point inside/outside/on boundary, emptiness,
          other region contained). Some geometric properties like size, or boundary size
          can be computed, as well as barycenters on the Euclidean space. Another important feature available for all these
          regions is the projection of a point to the closest region boundary (if there is a boundary). The projection provides
          both the projected point and the signed distance between the point and its projection, with the convention distance
          to boundary is considered negative if the point is inside the region, positive if the point is outside the region
          and of course 0 if the point is already on the boundary. This feature can be used for example as the value of a
          function in a root solver to determine when a moving point crosses the region boundary.
        </p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="11.2 Euclidean spaces" href="euclidean">
        <p>
          <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/oned/Vector1D.html">
          Vector1D</a>, <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/twod/Vector2D.html">
          Vector2D</a> and <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/threed/Vector3D.html">
          Vector3D</a> provide simple vector types. One important feature is
          that instances of these classes are guaranteed
          to be immutable, this greatly simplifies modeling dynamical systems
          with changing states: once a vector has been computed, a reference to it
          is known to preserve its state as long as the reference itself is preserved.
        </p>
        <p>
          Numerous constructors are available to create vectors. In addition to the
          straightforward Cartesian coordinates constructor, a constructor using
          azimuthal coordinates can build normalized vectors and linear constructors
          from one, two, three or four base vectors are also available. Constants have
          been defined for the most commons vectors (plus and minus canonical axes,
          null vector, and special vectors with infinite or NaN coordinates).
        </p>
        <p>
          The generic vectorial space operations are available including dot product,
          normalization, orthogonal vector finding and angular separation computation
          which have a specific meaning in 3D. The 3D geometry specific cross product
          is of course also implemented.
        </p>
        <p>
          <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/oned/Vector1DFormat.html">
          Vector1DFormat</a>, <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/twod/Vector2DFormat.html">
          Vector2DFormat</a> and <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/threed/Vector3DFormat.html">
          Vector3DFormat</a> are specialized classes for formatting output or parsing
          input with text representation of vectors.
        </p>
        <p>
          <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/threed/Rotation.html">
          Rotation</a> represents 3D rotations.
          Rotation instances are also immutable objects, as Vector3D instances.
        </p>
        <p>
          Rotations can be represented by several different mathematical
          entities (matrices, axe and angle, Cardan or Euler angles,
          quaternions). This class presents a higher level abstraction, more
          user-oriented and hiding implementation details. Well, for the
          curious, we use quaternions for the internal representation. The user
          can build a rotation from any of these representations, and any of
          these representations can be retrieved from a <code>Rotation</code>
          instance (see the various constructors and getters). In addition, a
          rotation can also be built implicitly from a set of vectors and their
          image.
        </p>
        <p>
          This implies that this class can be used to convert from one
          representation to another one. For example, converting a rotation
          matrix into a set of Cardan angles can be done using the
          following single line of code:
        </p>
        <source>double[] angles = new Rotation(matrix, 1.0e-10).getAngles(RotationOrder.XYZ);</source>
        <p>
          Focus is oriented on what a rotation <em>does</em> rather than on its
          underlying representation. Once it has been built, and regardless of
          its internal representation, a rotation is an <em>operator</em> which
          basically transforms three dimensional vectors into other three
          dimensional vectors. Depending on the application, the meaning of
          these vectors may vary as well as the semantics of the rotation.
        </p>
        <p>
          For example in a spacecraft attitude simulation tool, users will
          often consider the vectors are fixed (say the Earth direction for
          example) and the rotation transforms the coordinates coordinates of
          this vector in inertial frame into the coordinates of the same vector
          in satellite frame. In this case, the rotation implicitly defines the
          relation between the two frames (we have fixed vectors and moving frame).
          Another example could be a telescope control application, where the
          rotation would transform the sighting direction at rest into the desired
          observing direction when the telescope is pointed towards an object of
          interest. In this case the rotation transforms the direction at rest in
          a topocentric frame into the sighting direction in the same topocentric
          frame (we have moving vectors in fixed frame). In many case, both
          approaches will be combined, in our telescope example, we will probably
          also need to transform the observing direction in the topocentric frame
          into the observing direction in inertial frame taking into account the
          observatory location and the Earth rotation.
        </p>
        <p>
          These examples show that a rotation means what the user wants it to
          mean, so this class does not push the user towards one specific
          definition and hence does not provide methods like
          <code>projectVectorIntoDestinationFrame</code> or
          <code>computeTransformedDirection</code>. It provides simpler and more
          generic methods: <code>applyTo(Vector3D)</code> and
          <code>applyInverseTo(Vector3D)</code>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Since a rotation is basically a vectorial operator, several
          rotations can be composed together and the composite operation
          <code>r = r<sub>1</sub> o r<sub>2</sub></code> (which means that for each
          vector <code>u</code>, <code>r(u) = r<sub>1</sub>(r<sub>2</sub>(u))</code>)
          is also a rotation. Hence we can consider that in addition to vectors, a
          rotation can be applied to other rotations as well (or to itself). With our
          previous notations, we would say we can apply <code>r<sub>1</sub></code> to
          <code>r<sub>2</sub></code> and the result we get is <code>r =
          r<sub>1</sub> o r<sub>2</sub></code>. For this purpose, the class
          provides the methods: <code>applyTo(Rotation)</code> and
          <code>applyInverseTo(Rotation)</code>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="11.3 n-Sphere" href="sphere">
        <p>
          The Apache Commons Math library provides a few classes dealing with geometry
          on the 1-sphere (i.e. the one dimensional circle corresponding to the boundary of
          a two-dimensional disc) and the 2-sphere (i.e. the two dimensional sphere surface
          corresponding to the boundary of a three-dimensional ball). The main classes in
          this package correspond to the region explained above, i.e.
          <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/spherical/oned/ArcsSet.html">ArcsSet</a>
          and <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/spherical/twod/SphericalPolygonsSet.html">SphericalPolygonsSet</a>.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="11.4 Binary Space Partitioning" href="partitioning">
        <p>
          <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/partitioning/BSPTree.html">
          BSP trees</a> are an efficient way to represent space partitions and
          to associate attributes with each cell. Each node in a BSP tree
          represents a convex region which is partitioned in two convex
          sub-regions at each side of a cut hyperplane. The root tree
          contains the complete space.
        </p>

        <p>
          The main use of such partitions is to use a boolean attribute to
          define an inside/outside property, hence representing arbitrary
          polytopes (line segments in 1D, polygons in 2D and polyhedrons in
          3D) and to operate on them. This is how the regions explained above in the Euclidean
          and Sphere spaces are implemented. The partitioning package provides the engine to do the
          computation, but not the dimension-specific implementations. The
          various interfaces in this package (hyperplane, sub-hyperplane, embedding,
          and even region) are therefore not considered to be reusable public
          interface, they are private interface. They may change and users are not expected to
          rely directly on them. What users can rely on is the BSP tree class itself, and the
          space-specific implementations of the interfaces (i.e. Plane in 3D as the implementation
          of hyperplane, or S2Point on the 2-Sphere as the implementation of Point).
        </p>

        <p>
          Another example of BST tree use would be to represent Voronoi tesselations, the
          attribute of each cell holding the defining point of the cell. This is not
          available yet.
        </p>

        <p>
          The application-defined attributes are shared among copied
          instances and propagated to split parts. These attributes are not
          used by the BSP-tree algorithms themselves, so the application can
          use them for any purpose. Since the tree visiting method holds
          internal and leaf nodes differently, it is possible to use
          different classes for internal nodes attributes and leaf nodes
          attributes. This should be used with care, though, because if the
          tree is modified in any way after attributes have been set, some
          internal nodes may become leaf nodes and some leaf nodes may become
          internal nodes.
        </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="11.5 Regions">
        <p>
          The regions in all Euclidean and spherical spaces are based on BSP-tree using a <code>Boolean</code>
          attribute in the leaf cells representing the inside status of the corresponding cell
          (true for inside cells, false for outside cells). They all need a <code>tolerance</code> setting that
          is either provided at construction when the region is built from scratch or inherited from the input
          regions when a region is build by set operations applied to other regions. This setting is used when
          the region itself will be used later in another set operation or when points are tested against the
          region to compute inside/outside/on boundary status. This tolerance is the <em>thickness</em>
          of the hyperplane. Points closer than this value to a boundary hyperplane will be considered
          <em>on boundary</em>. There are no default values anymore for this setting (there was one when
          BSP-tree support was introduced, but it created more problems than it solved, so it has been intentionally
          removed). Setting this tolerance really depends on the expected values for the various coordinates. If for
          example the region is used to model a geological structure with a scale of a few thousand meters, the expected
          coordinates order of magnitude will be about 10<sup>3</sup> and the tolerance could be set to 10<sup>-7</sup>
          (i.e.  0.1 micrometer) or above. If very thin triangles or nearly parallel lines occur, it may be safer to use
          a larger value like 10<sup>-3</sup> for example. Of course if the BSP-tree is used to model a crystal at
          atomic level with coordinates of the order of magnitude about 10<sup>-9</sup> the tolerance should be
          drastically reduced (perhaps down to 10<sup>-20</sup> or so).
        </p>
        <p>
          The recommended way to build regions is to start from basic shapes built from their boundary representation
          and to use the set operations to combine these basic shapes into more complex shapes. The basic shapes
          that can be constructed from boundary representations must have a closed boundary and be in one part
          without holes. Regions in several non-connected parts or with holes must be built by building the parts
          beforehand and combining them. All regions (<code>IntervalsSet</code>, <code>PolygonsSet</code>,
          <code>PolyhedronsSet</code>, <code>ArcsSet</code>, <code>SphericalPolygonsSet</code>) provide a dedicated
          constructor using only the mandatory tolerance distance without any other parameters that always create
          the region covering the full space. The empty region case, can be built by building first the full space
          region and applying the <code>RegionFactory.getComplement()</code> method to it to get the corresponding
          empty region, it can also be built directly for a one-cell BSP-tree as explained below.
        </p>
        <p>
          Another way to build regions is to create directly the underlying BSP-tree. All regions (<code>IntervalsSet</code>,
          <code>PolygonsSet</code>, <code>PolyhedronsSet</code>, <code>ArcsSet</code>, <code>SphericalPolygonsSet</code>)
          provide a dedicated constructor that accepts a BSP-tree and a tolerance. This way to build regions should be
          reserved to dimple cases like the full space, the empty space of regions with only one or two cut hyperplances.
          It is not recommended in the general case and is considered expert use. The leaf nodes of the BSP-tree
          <em>must</em> have a <code>Boolean</code> attribute representing the inside status of the corresponding cell
          (true for inside cells, false for outside cells). In order to avoid building too many small objects, it is
          recommended to use the predefined constants <code>Boolean.TRUE</code> and <code>Boolean.FALSE</code>. Using
          this method, one way to build directly an empty region without complementing the full region is as follows
          (note the tolerance parameter which must be present even for the empty region):
        </p>
        <source>
PolygonsSet empty = new PolygonsSet(new BSPTree&lt;Euclidean2D&gt;(false), tolerance);
        </source>
        <p>
         In the Euclidean 3D case, the <a href="../apidocs/org/apache/commons/math4/geometry/euclidean/threed/PolyhedronsSet.html">PolyhedronsSet</a>
         class has another specific constructor to build regions from vertices and facets. The signature of this
         constructor is:
        </p>
        <source>
PolyhedronsSet(List&lt;Vector3D&gt; vertices, List&lt;int[]&gt; facets, double tolerance);
        </source>
        <p>
          The vertices list contains all the vertices of the polyhedrons, the facets list defines the facets,
          as an indirection in the vertices list. Each facet is a short integer array and each element in a
          facet array is the index of one vertex in the list. So in our cube example, the vertices list would
          contain 8 points corresponding to the cube vertices, the facets list would contain 6 facets (the sides
          of the cube) and each facet would contain 4 integers corresponding to the indices of the 4 vertices
          defining one side. Of course, each vertex would be referenced once in three different facets.
        </p>
        <p>
          Beware that despite some basic consistency checks are performed in the constructor, not everything
          is checked, so it remains under caller responsibility to ensure the vertices and facets are consistent
          and properly define a polyhedrons set. One particular trick is that when defining a facet, the vertices
          <em>must</em> be provided as walking the polygons boundary in <em>trigonometric</em> order (i.e.
          counterclockwise) as seen from the *external* side of the facet. The reason for this is that the walking
          order does define the orientation of the inside and outside parts, so walking the boundary on the wrong
          order would reverse the facet and the polyhedrons would not be the one you intended to define. Coming
          back to our cube example, a logical orientation of the facets would define the polyhedrons as the finite
          volume within the cube to be the inside and the infinite space surrounding the cube as the outside, but
          reversing all facets would also define a perfectly well behaved polyhedrons which would have the infinite
          space surrounding the cube as its inside and the finite volume within the cube as its outside!
        </p>
        <p>
          If one wants to further look at how it works, there is a test parser for PLY file formats in the unit tests
          section of the library and some basic ply files for a simple geometric shape (the N pentomino) in the test
          resources. This parser uses the constructor defined above as the PLY file format uses vertices and facets
          to represent 3D shapes.
        </p>
       </subsection>
     </section>
  </body>
</document>
