<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Tasks: Done And To Do</title>
 </properties>

 <body>
  <section name='Aim'>
   <p>
    This page aims to be a handy reference not only of the work done but 
    also of work pending for the next planned release. Users who want new 
    features should submit patches to this page in the unclassified section
    of this document. Developers who want to lend a hand can grab tasks from 
    this page. Everyone can see the progress which is being made.
   </p>
  </section>
    
  <section name="TODO list">
   <p>
    The following is a list of items still <code>TODO</code> for 
    Math.  Contributions are welcome! 
   </p>
    
   <subsection name="High priority"> 
    <ul>
     <li>
      <strong>Fill Me In!</strong>
      With A High Priority Task
     </li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>
    
   <subsection name="Medium priority"> 
    <ul>
     <li>
      <strong>Fill Me In</strong>
      With A Medium Priority Task
     </li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>
    
   <subsection name="Low priority"> 
    <ul>
     <li>
      <strong>Fill Me In</strong>
      With A Low Priority Task
     </li>
    </ul>
   </subsection>

   <subsection name="Unclassified priority"> 
    <ul>
     <li>
      Add confidence intervals to Univariate implementations.
     </li>     
     <li> Extend distribution framework to support discrete distributions and 
      implement binomial and hypergeometric distributions.
     </li>
     <li>
      Framework and implementation strategie(s) for finding roots or real-valued
      functions of one (real) variable.
     </li>
     <li>
      Cubic spline interpolation.
     </li>
     <li>
      Javadoc generation is still throwing warnings.  Bring the 
      Javadoc into compliance (i.e. reach zero warnings).
     </li>
     <li>
      Clover tests show gaps in test path coverage. Get all tests to
      100% coverage.  Also improve test data and boundary conditions coverage.
     </li>
     <li>
      CheckStyle with modified properties still shows many errors.  Clean these
      up.
     </li>
     <li>
      Develop user's guide following the package structure.
     </li>
     <li>Additional performance and accuracy testing. If anyone is interested 
      in helping out here, what we could really use is a wider selection of 
      test cases for the core numerical functions and validation against either 
      other packages (e.g. R for the statistical stuff), verified datasets, 
      or experiments comparing implementions using floats to doubles.
     </li>
     <li>
       Additional code review. Verify that the code matches the 
       documentation and identify obvious inefficiencies or numerical problems.  
       All feedback/suggestions for improvement/patches are welcome.
     </li>
     <li>
      Finalize the contents of MathUtils and StatUtils. Suggest any additions 
      -- ideally with patches --  to these utility classes.
     </li> 
    </ul>
   </subsection>

  </section>
  <section name='Completed'>
   <subsection name='Since Conception'>
    <ul>
    <li>
      Bivariate Regression, correlation. 
    </li>
    <li>
      Sampling from Collections
    </li>
    <li>
      Add higher order moments to Univariate implementations.
    </li>
    <li>
      Binomial coefficients -- incorporate an "exact" implementation that is
      limited to what can be stored in a long.  Also provided double-valued
      implementation of binomial coefficients and their logs.
    </li>
    <li>
      Add percentiles to stored Univariate implementations
    </li>
    <li>
     Improve numerical accuracy of Univariate and BivariateRegression statistical
     computations
     </li>
     <li>
      t-test statistic needs to be added and we should probably add the
      capability of actually performing t- and chi-square tests at fixed
      significance levels (.1, .05, .01, .001).
     </li>
     <li>
      numerical approximation of the t- and chi-square distributions to
      enable user-supplied significance levels.      
     </li>
     <li>
      The RealMatrixImpl class is missing some key method implementations.
      The critical thing is solution of linear systems.  We need to implement a 
      numerically sound solution algorithm.  This will enable inverse() and also
      support general linear regression.
     </li>
     <li>
      Added double[] |-> double methods in StatUtils to take start indexes and length
      as parameters and delegate the current "full array" versions to these.
     </li>    
    </ul>
   </subsection>
  </section>
 </body>
</document>

