<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!--
   Copyright 2003-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

   Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
   you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
   You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
  
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xdoc.xsl"?>
<!-- $Revision: 1.20 $ $Date: 2004/04/27 04:37:59 $ -->
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Tasks: Done And To Do</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Aim">
      <p>This page aims to be a handy reference not only of the work done but also of work pending for the next planned release. 
      Users who want new features should submit patches to this page in the unclassified section of this document. 
      Developers who want to lend a hand can grab tasks from this page. Everyone can see the progress which is being made.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="TODO list">
      <p>The following is a list of items still <code>TODO</code> for Math.  Contributions are welcome!</p>
      <subsection name="Documentation and Code Conformance Tasks">
        <p>Many of these will always be a required. Please focus on applying format standards and provide as many 
        test cases as possible for your code.</p>
        <dl>
          <dt>Develop user's guide following the package structure.</dt>
          <dd>Incomplete Sections:  1.5 Statistical Tests, 3.1 Linear Algebra Overview, 3.2 Real Matrices, 3.3 Solving Linear Systems, 6.1 Utilities Overview, 6.2 Double Array Utilities, 6.4 Binomial Coefficients, ..., 6.5 Statistical Computation Utilities, 7.4 Complex Formatting</dd>
          <dt>Performance and accuracy testing.</dt>
          <dd>If anyone is interested in helping out here, what we could really use is a wider selection of test cases for the core
           numerical functions and validation against either other packages (e.g. R for the statistical stuff), verified datasets,
           or experiments comparing implementions using floats to doubles.</dd>
          <dt>Test Coverage.</dt>
          <dd>Clover tests show gaps in test path coverage. Get all tests to 100% coverage.  Also improve test data and 
           boundary conditions coverage.</dd>
          <dt>Code review.</dt>
          <dd>
            <p>Code review is a continuous process that all Contributors and Developers should practice while working on the code base.</p>
            <ul>
              <li>Javadoc generation is still throwing warnings.  Bring the Javadoc into compliance (i.e. reach zero warnings).</li>
              <li>Verify that the code matches the documentation and identify obvious inefficiencies or numerical problems.  All feedback/suggestions for improvement/patches are welcome.</li>
              <li>CheckStyle with modified properties still shows many errors.  Try to clean these up.</li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
          <dt>Javadoc</dt>
          <dd>Bring all javadoc up to requirements in the <a href="developers.html">Developer's Guide</a></dd>
          <dd>Run linkcheck and fix all broken links in Javadoc</dd>
        </dl>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Algorithm Development Tasks">
        <p>These current tasks are planned and need completion for the inital release</p>
        <dl>
         <dt>Root Finding</dt>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>Rework unit tests for root finding</li>
              <li>CheckStyle with modified properties still shows many errors.  Try to clean these up.</li>
              <li>Finalize API (maybe move to stateless implementation)</li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
        
        <dt>Complex Number Library</dt>
          <dd>
              An initial <a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/show_bug.cgi?id=24241">submission</a>
              of a complex number library has been donated by Brent Worden. It has been added 
              and is open to be reviewed/tested by others for feedback. 
              The implementation is based on the following source:
              <a href="http://myweb.lmu.edu/dmsmith/ZMLIB.pdf">http://myweb.lmu.edu/dmsmith/ZMLIB.pdf</a>.            
              <ul>
                  <li><a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/eyebrowse/ReadMsg?listId=15&amp;msgNo=28132">
                      Thread Subject: [math] Complex dilemmas
                  </a></li>
                  <li><a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/eyebrowse/ReadMsg?listName=commons-dev@jakarta.apache.org&amp;msgNo=36293">
                      Thread Subject: [math] Complex implementation
                  </a></li>
              </ul>
          </dd>
        <dt>RealMatrix</dt>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>Implement rank() method or drop from interface.</li>
            </ul>
          </dd> 
        <dt>BeanList Statistics</dt>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>Refactor BeanList statistics, find appropriate package placement</li>
            </ul>
          </dd> 
        </dl>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Future Goals">
      <subsection name="Delayed Tasks slated for the next release of the Math library">
      <dl> 
        <dt>Statistics</dt>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>More inference methods</li>
              <li>Multiple regression</li>
            </ul>
          </dd> 
          <dt>Linear Algebra</dt>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>More matrix decompositions (Cholesky, QR, SVD) and framework to support.</li>
              <li>Sparse matrices</li>
            </ul>
          </dd> 
        </dl> 
      </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
